Finding Aid for Thomas Francis Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- Organizations, 1938-1969; 22 linear feet
  - American Medical Association
    - 1949-1950 (Box 25)
    - 1951-1961 (Box 25)
    - Committee on Biological Agents of a Hazardous Nature, 1949 (Box 25)
  - American Philosophical Society
    - 1954-1969 (Box 25)
    - Membership Committee, 1961-1966 (Box 25)
  - American Public Health Association (Box 26)
    - General, 1940-1948 (Box 26)
    - General, 1949-1950 (Box 26)
    - General, 1951-1959 (Box 26)
    - Committees/Sub-committees
      - Administrative Practice
        (also Subcommittee on the Evaluation of Administrative Practice)
        - General, 1947 (Box 26)
        - Re Study Committee on Influenza Vaccination (Box 26)
      - Air Sanitation, 1947-1950 (Box 26)
      - Laboratory Methods, Coordinating Committee on, 1944-1956; 4 folders (Box 26)
        (also Subcommittee on Diagnostic Procedures on Virus and Rickettsial Methods)
      - Research and Standards
        - 1943-1950, 3 folders (Box 26)
        - Re Pearl Kendrick and her work on pertussis, 1948-1950 (Box 26)
      - Technical Development Board, 1958-1960 (Box 26)
    - Sections
      - Epidemiology Section, 1951-1969; 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Industrial Hygiene, 1947-1949 (Box 26)
        (with AMA and USPHA)
    - Governing Council and Executive Board, 1948-1964; 0.7 linear feet (Box 27)
      (unprocessed)
  - American Society for Clinical Investigation (Box 28)
    - 1938-1945 (Box 28)
    - 1946 (Box 28)
    - 1947-1950 (Box 28)
    - 1951-1959 (Box 28)
  - American Society for Experimental Pathology, 1952-1956 (Box 28)
  - American Society for Microbiology
    - 1960-1965 (Box 28)
    - 1968 (Box 28)
  - American Trudeau Society. Technical Committee on Acute Respiratory Diseases, 1959-1960 (Box 28)
  - Army Medical Service Graduate School, 1951-1953 (Box 39)
  - Association of American Physicians
    - 1941-1948 (Box 39)
    - 1951-1959 (Box 39)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 39)
      (scattered)
  - Association of Schools of Public Health
    - 1941-1945 (Box 39)
    - Accreditation Committee, 1941-1947 (Box 39)
  - Atomic Bomb Casualty Committee, 1955-1969; 0.7 linear feet (Box 39)
  - Biological warfare defense, 1951-1956; 3 folders (Box 40)
    (various organizations)
    - Correspondence with Collaborating Laboratories, 1951-1952 (Box 40)
      (includes correspondence of Jonas Salk)
  - Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1957-1962 (Box 40)
  - Cholera, 6 linear feet (Box 40)
    (various organizations, NIH Cholera Advisory Committee, 1965 Symposium on Cholera Research, and Pakistan-SEATO Cholera Research Laboratory)
  - Clinical Research, Central Society for, 1945-1948 (Box 40)
  - Common Cold Institute
    - 1949-1954 (Box 40)
    - 1955-1957 (Box 40)
  - Common Cold Institute (Box 41)
    - 1958 (Box 41)
    - 1959 (Box 41)
  - Communicable Disease Center
    (USPHS)
    - General (Box 41)
    - Influenza Surveillance Committee (Box 41)
  - Constantinian Society
    - 1949-1950 (Box 41)
    - 1951-1959 (Box 41)
  - Cosmos Club, 1953-1968; 3 folders (Box 41)
  - Drug Safety, Commission on, 1962-1965; 0.5 linear feet (Box 41)
  - Ecological Study Commission (Box 42)
  - Epidemiological survey, ad hoc committee on the, 1950-1955; 2 folders (Box 42)
  - Epidemiology and Biometry, Advisory Committee on, 1956-1960; 0.5 linear feet (Box 42)
  - Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (Box 42)
  - Infectious Diseases Society of America (Box 42)
  - Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research, 1947-1968 (Box 43)
  - Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research, 1947-1968 (Box 44)
  - Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research, 1947-1968; 0.6 linear feet (Box 45)
  - Life Science, ad hoc committee on, 1965-1966
    - Meeting, 1965 (Box 45)
    - Meeting, 1966 (Box 45)
    - Hesburgh, Theodore (Box 45)
    - Rossini, F.D (Box 45)
  - Lobund Institute, 1958-1965 (Box 45)
  - Medical Bacteriologists, Steering Committee for the Accreditation of, 0.6 linear feet (Box 46)
  - Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs, 0.2 linear feet (Box 46)
  - Microbiology, Ad hoc Committee on Sectional Research in, 0.2 linear feet (Box 46)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 0.5 linear feet (Box 47)
  - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis
    - Reports of the U-M Dept. of Epidemiology to the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, July 1941-June 1958 (Box 47)
      (annual/semi-annual reports)
    - Reports of the U-M Dept. of Epidemiology to the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, July 1958-June 1964 (Box 48)
    - International Poliomyletis Conferences
      - 1948 (Box 48)
        (1st)
      - 1951 (Box 48)
        (2nd)
      - 1954 (Box 48)
        (3rd)
      - 1957 (Box 48)
        (4th)
    - Proceedings of round-table conferences, committees, etc (Box 49)
    - Proceedings of round-table conferences, committees, etc (Box 50)
    - Poliomyelitis
      (miscellaneous)
      - East Hospital Sanitary Sewage Disposal Company report, January-July 1943 (Box 50)
      - Minnesota poliomyelitis study, 1946 (Box 50)
      - Gamma globulin prophylaxis study, Freeport, Illinois, 1945-1946 (Box 50)
      - Sister Kenny treatment, 1944-1946 (Box 50)
      - Meetings (Box 50)
        (various)
      - Maps showing distribution of poliomyelitis (Box 50)
    - Poliomyelitis cases
      - Yearly summaries and related, 1944-1951; 10 folders (Box 51)
    - Dated files
      - 1941-1947
        - Budgets, accounting sheets, etc (Box 51)
        - Correspondence
          - Gudakunst (Don)/Kingdon (Carolyn) (Box 51)
          - O'Connor, Basil (Box 51)
          - Van Riper, Hart E (Box 51)
          - Weaver, H.M (Box 51)
          - Various (Charlock, Lavan, Kelly, etc.) (Box 51)
      - 1948-1950
        - Budgets, accounting sheets, etc., 1948-1949 (Box 51)
        - Correspondence
          - Weaver, H.M (Box 51)
          - Various (Box 51)
      - 1950-1954
        - Correspondence
          - Weaver, H.M (Box 51)
          - Various (Box 51)
      - 1955-1965
        - Correspondence
          - Kumm, Henry W., 1955-1959 (Box 51)
          - Rivers, Thomas (Box 51)
            (Polio Advisory Committee)
          - Van Riper, Hart E., 1955-1956 (Box 51)
          - Various (Box 51)
  - National Institutes of Health. Committee on Influenza Research, 1957-1962; 0.5 linear feet (Box 52)
    (includes Subcommittee of Investigators)
  - National Institutes of Health. Polio Technical Committee, 1957-1959; 3 folders (Box 52)
  - National Institutes of Health. Virus and Rickettsial Section (Box 52)
  - National Library of Medicine (Box 52)
  - National Research Council. Division of Medical Sciences, 1951-1954; 3 folders (Box 52)
  - National Sanitation Foundation, 1965-1966; 2 folders (Box 52)
    (Man versus Environment Congress)
  - National Tuberculosis Association, 1950 (Box 52)
  - Preventive Medicine
    - Association of Professors of Preventive Medicine, 1953-1958 (Box 52)
    - Conference of Professors of Preventive Medicine, 1946-1948 (Box 52)
    - Interim Board for Preventive Medicine, 1948 (Box 52)
  - Rheumatic Fever Control Committee, Michigan State Medical Society, 1947-1959; 4 folders (Box 53)
  - Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine
    - 1940-1958 (Box 53)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 53)
  - Space Science, Committee on the Biological Aspects of, 1959-1960 (Box 53)
  - U.S.-Japan Cooperative Medical Science Program, 1965-1969 (Box 53)
    (.6 lin. ft. unprocessed)
  - U.S.-Japan Cooperative Medical Science Program, 1965-1969; 0.5 linear feet (Box 54)
  - U.S.-Philippines Workshop on Science Cooperation and Development, 1965; 0.2 linear feet (Box 54)
  - Vaccine Development Committee, National Institutes of Health, 1965-1975; 0.3 linear feet (Box 54)
  - Vaccine Development Committee, National Institutes of Health, 1965-1975 (Box 55)
  - Vaccine Development Committee, National Institutes of Health, 1965-1975; 0.5 linear feet (Box 56)
  - Veterans Administration Hospital, Ann Arbor, Michigan. Research and Education Committee, 1953-1959; 2 folders (Box 56)
  - Washtenaw County Medical Society. Poliomyelitis Committee (Box 56)
- University of Michigan, 1941-1969; 3 linear feet
  University of Michigan, 1941-1969 (3 linear feet). This smaller series relates specifically to Francis' responsibilities as a member of the faculty of the University of Michigan. As a respected scientist and scholar, Francis was called upon to serve on such university-wide or cross-unit committees as the Cancer Research Institute Committee, the Mental Health Research Institute Advisory Committee, the Henry Russel Lecture Committee, and the Senate Advisory Committee. In addition, this series contains files relating to his work within the School of Public Health. Noteworthy here are records maintained by Francis on the extensive study undertaken by the School of Public Health on the state of public health in the small community of Tecumseh, Michigan.
  - Senate Advisory Committee (Box 56)
  - Programs and committees (Box 56)
  - Henry Russel Lecture Committee, 0.3 linear feet (Box 57)
  - Cancer Research Institute Committee, 1954-1969; 0.7 linear feet (Box 57)
  - Cancer Research Institute Committee, 1954-1969; 0.5 linear feet (Box 58)
  - Mental Health Research Institute Advisory Committee (Box 58)
  - Division of Health Sciences-Biological (Box 58)
  - University of Michigan School of Public Health
    - Committee for selection of new dean (Box 58)
    - Miscellaneous committees (Box 58)
    - Re sabbaticals (Box 58)
    - Tecumseh Community Health Study, 1959-1961; 0.6 linear feet (Box 59)
- Speeches, articles, etc, 1928-1969; 4 linear feet
  Speeches, articles, etc., 1928-1969 (4 linear feet). Like Organizations, this series is also a bringing together of similar kinds of files. Francis was a prolific writer, speaker, and attendee at professional conferences. In this series have been gathered files pertaining to symposia and conferences attended, reprints of articles, speeches and outlines of talks, and a scattering of some of the materials Francis used as an instructor at the University (1938-1940 only).
  - Symposia and conference papers (Box 59)
    - 1930-1956, 1959-1960 (Box 59)
    - 1961-1965 (Box 60)
    - 1966-1969 (Box 61)
  - Reprints of articles, 1928-1969; 3 volumes, 1 folder (Box 62)
  - Calendar of activities, 1941; 1951-1962 (Box 62)
  - Instructors notes, 1938-1940 (Box 63)
  - Outlines and notes of talks, 1942-1961; 1968 (Box 63)
    (includes laminated fragment of announcement of success of polio vaccine)
- Topical files, 1925-1967; 1 linear foot
  Topical files, 1925-1967 (1 linear ft.) is a small series consisting of various materials not easily assimilated into the principal series of the Francis papers, e.g. material on the Committee for a National Science Foundation and on a post-war epidemiology course.
  - Asian Influenza, 1957 (Box 63)
  - Cole, Rufus, 1966-1967
    (correspondence and background material largely concerning TF's speech honoring Cole)
    - Background, 2 folders (Box 63)
    - Kovalenko Award (Box 63)
    - Cole Lecture, 1967 (Box 63)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 64)
  - Committee for a National Science Foundation, 1943-1946 (Box 64)
  - Diagnostic Procedures for Virus and Rickettsial Diseases, 1946-1956; 1 folder (Box 64)
    (correspondence and other materials relating to publication of various editions of book)
  - Hepatitis research (Coral City, Michigan), 1944-1945 (Box 64)
  - National Research Foundation, 1945-1946 (Box 64)
    (correspondence, with Homer Smith concerning science legislation and the founding of the N.R.F.)
  - Post-war epidemiology, 1944 (Box 64)
    (U-M in-service training course,)
  - Yale University course materials, circa 1925 (Box 64)
- Personal/Biographical, 1917-1969; 2 linear feet
  Personal/Biographical, 1917-1969 (2 linear ft.) is an artificial series comprised of biographical and personal information about Francis, including newspaper clippings about his life, scrapbooks of clippings, various early research materials, and photographs.
  - Appointments (Box 65)
  - Awards, diplomas, etc. (Box 65)
    (See also oversize folder)
  - Biographical (Box 65)
  - Bibliographical (Box 65)
  - Condolences, 1969-1970; 2 folders (Box 65)
  - High school yearbook, 1917 (Box 65)
    (Newcastle, PA)
  - History/Reminiscences, no date (Box 65)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1940s-1970s; 3 folders (Box 65)
  - Photographs, 1950s-1969
    - Associates and friends, 3 folders (Box 65)
    - Groups (Box 65)
    - Various, 1950s-1969 (Box 65)
  - Scrapbooks, 1941-1972; 2 folders (Box 65)
    (includes obituaries and memorials, photos, clippings, and related materials)
  - Research notes, laboratory reports, etc (Box 66)